Guide to the Rice University Assistant to the President papers: Mark Scheid, 1999-2006 UA 302
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Assistant to the President papers: Mark Scheid
1999-2006
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 302
1.3 Linear Feet (2 cartons)
Correspondence, news clippings, contracts, speeches, reports, minutes, and other types of documents used in conducting the business of the President's Office from the Assistant to the President, Mark Scheid 1999-2006.
Biographical Note
Mark Scheid earned his undergraduate degree in English at Rice University in 1967 and his doctorate in English literature in 1972. He joined Texas Southern University (TSU) as an assistant professor of English in 1971 and became an associate professor there in 1978 and a full professor in 1985. He became a visiting professor of English at Rice in 1984 and held numerious academic advising and administrative posts including assistant vice president for student affairs and Director of Academic Advising and International Programs.
Scheid assumed the position of assistant to the president on November 1, 1999. He worked with Carl MacDowell during a transition period until MacDowell's tenure ended January 31, 2000. He served the Office of the President during two administrations - Malcolm Gillis (1993-2004) and David Leebron (2004-present) before filling the newly created position of managing director for programs and international studies at the James A. Baker III Institute for Public Policy in 2006.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the records are paper documents made up of correspondence, news clippings, contracts, speeches, reports, minutes, financial documents, and other types of documents used in conducting the business of the President's Office. There are also documents from Carl MacDowell's tenure as assistant to the presdent forwarded to Mark Scheid during the transitional period before Scheid replaced him.
Access Restrictions
Permission to access the President's Office Records must be obtained in writing from the Office of the President. Legal and disciplinary files need special permission.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Arrangement
The dates noted on each folder cover the time span of the contents of the material located inside. In some cases older documents probably used in researching the subject or that had been retained by several administrations, were included in the folders. Sometimes overlapping dates may be found in more than one folder.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges
Document Types
minutes (administrative records)
Places
Rice University
- Series I: Academic Departments, Institutes, and Centers, 158186
  Scope and Contents note
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by name of department. Contents of the folders are mostly in original order and the dates that are covered are noted on the folder.
  - Anthropology - Archaeological Field School, Goree, 2005; 158185 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baker Institute for Public Policy (BIPP), 1994-95; 158190 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: On Campus - General, 157800
  The material in this series is filed alphabetically by administrative offices or heading. Original order was maintained so there may be overlapping of dates on some folders.
  - Academic/Promotion/Tenure Information, 1999; 158176 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academy Members, 1998; 158177 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Administrative Officers, 1999; 158178 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Admissions, 1995; 158179 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Admissions - Student Athletes, 1990-92; 158180 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Admissions - Student Athletes, 1993; 158181 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Admissions - Student Athletes, 1994; 158182 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Admissions - Student Athletes, 1995; 158183 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Admissions - Student Athletes, 1995; 158184 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Admissions - Student Athletes, 2001-02; 158194 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Athletics - Anderson Audit, 2000; 158195 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Athletics, 2000; 158196 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Athletics (1 of 2), 2003; 158197 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Athletics (2 of 2), 2003; 158198 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Athletics, 2004; 158199 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Athletics - Legal Counsel, 1999, 2003-04; 158200 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Athletics - Pro Forma, 1995; 158201 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Athletics - Survey Results, 2004; 158202 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Athletics - Facilities, 2001; 158203 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Athletics - Financial Aid, 2001-02; 158204 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Athletics - Gender Equity, 2001; 158205 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Athletics - NACDA Director's Cup Division I Final Standings, 2002-03; 158206 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Athletics - NCAA Division I Self Study Report, 1999; 158207 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Athletics - NCAA Division I Self Study Report, 1999; 158208 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Athletics - Price Waterhouse Cooper Audit, 2003; 158209 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Athletics - Southwest Conference (SWC) Graduation Rates, 1983-84, 1984-85; 158210 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Athletics - NCAA/ Graduation Rates, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Athletics - Team GPAs, Fall 2003; 158211 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Board of Trustees' Briefings, 1999-2000; 158212 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Board of Trustees' Subcommittee on Athletics, 2003-04; 158230 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Budget/Endowment/Revenues Information, 1998; 158213 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Budget, 2000; 158214 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Committees - Assignments, 1995-96; 158215 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Committees - Athletics, 2000; 158216 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Committees - Athletics, Report on Athletics and Homosexuality, 2004; 158217 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Committees - Athletics Review Committee Report, 1992; 158218 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Committees - Athletics Review Committee, 2001-02; 158219 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Committees - China International Committee, 2005-06; 158221 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Committees - Faculty Council Committee on Athletics (FCCA), 2003-04; 158223 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Committees - FCCA - final report, 1992; 158224 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Committees - FCCA - report, 2003; 158226 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Committees - University Standing Committees, 1995-96; 158232 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Degrees Earned, 1995; 158234 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Development, 1994-95; 158235 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Enrollment, [1999]; 158236 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Facilities, 1993-95; 158237 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Factsheet, 1995; 158238 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Faculty, 1994-95; 158239 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Chairs, 1995; 158240 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Leaves, 1993-97; 158241 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Salaries, 1993-99; 158242 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Statistics (legal size folder), 1994-99; 158243 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Counsel, 2000; 158244 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gillis, Malcom/David Auston meeting agendas, 1997-99; 158245 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Goals, 1994; 158246 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Leadership Rice Summer Mentorship Experience, 2004; 158247 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Operations Council, 1999-2000; 158248 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photographs - Hill County, 1998; 158249 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Questia Contract, 2001; 158250 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Special Assistant to Vice President for Public Affairs, 1999; 158251 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Staff Salaries, 1995; 158252 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Student Charges, 1995; 158253 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, 1995-97; 158254 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, March-August 1999; 158255 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, September 1999; 158256 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, October 1999; 158261 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, November 1999; 158257 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, November 1999; 158260 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, December 1999; 158258 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material, January 2000; 158259 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Transition to Assistant to President material - Budget, 1999; 158434 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series III: Off Campus - General, 157801
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title of off campus organizations and other groups that were not an immediate part of Rice University.
  - Association of American Universities (AAU) Council on Federal Relations Directory, June 1999; 158262 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - International University Bremen, March-July 2000; 158263 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - International University Bremen, August-November 2000; 158264 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - International University Bremen, 2001; 158265 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Main Street Theater, 2000; 158266 (Box 2, Folder 34)